<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R maps on Teoten&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.teoten.com/tags/r-maps/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R maps on Teoten&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.teoten.com/tags/r-maps/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Map any region in the world with R - Part III: Programming with ggplot2</title>
      <link>https://blog.teoten.com/posts/2023/map_any_region_with_ggplot2_part_iii/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.teoten.com/posts/2023/map_any_region_with_ggplot2_part_iii/</guid>
      <description>This post is part of the series maps-app.
You can also find the current state of the project under my GitHub repo mapic.
Scope of this post We are creating maps of data showing changes over a span of time for different countries and pointing at all kinds of cities. That basically means that we need to map any region of the world with R.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Webscrap and iteration in R</title>
      <link>https://blog.teoten.com/posts/2023/webscrap_and_iteration_in_r/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.teoten.com/posts/2023/webscrap_and_iteration_in_r/</guid>
      <description>About this post We are creating maps of data showing changes over a span of time for different countries and pointing at all kinds of cities. That basically means that we need to map any region of the world with R. Today there are all kinds of packages and techniques to do that.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Webscrap e iteraciones con R</title>
      <link>https://blog.teoten.com/es/posts/2023/webscrap_and_iteration_in_r/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.teoten.com/es/posts/2023/webscrap_and_iteration_in_r/</guid>
      <description>Sobre este post Estamos creando mapas de datos que muestran los cambios durante un período de tiempo para diferentes países y orientado a todo tipo de ciudades. Esto básicamente significa que necesitamos mapear cualquier región del mundo con R. Hoy en día existen todo tipo de paquetes y técnicas para hacerlo.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Map any region in the world with R - Part II: Obtaining the coordinates</title>
      <link>https://blog.teoten.com/posts/2022/map_any_region_with_ggplot2_part_ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.teoten.com/posts/2022/map_any_region_with_ggplot2_part_ii/</guid>
      <description>This post is part of the series maps-app.
You can also find the current state of the project under my GitHub repo mapic.
Scope of this post This is the second part of the series to create a map of any region of the world with R.
We are creating maps of data showing changes over a span of time for different countries and pointing at all kinds of cities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapa de cualquier región del mundo con R - Parte II: obteniendo las coordenadas.</title>
      <link>https://blog.teoten.com/es/posts/2022/map_any_region_with_ggplot2_part_ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.teoten.com/es/posts/2022/map_any_region_with_ggplot2_part_ii/</guid>
      <description>Pueden encontrar todas las publicaciones en este tema bajo las series maps-app.
También pueden encontrar el estado actual del proyecto en mi GitHub repo mapic.
Sobre este post Esta es la segunda parte de las series de cómo crear mapas de cualquier región del mundo con R. De antemano me disculpo por detalles que puedan encontrar en la traducción, el post original lo creé en Inglés y el trabajo de traducción puede ser excesivo si voy a cada detalle.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Map any region in the world with R - Part I: The basic map</title>
      <link>https://blog.teoten.com/posts/2022/map_any_region_with_ggplot2_part_i/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.teoten.com/posts/2022/map_any_region_with_ggplot2_part_i/</guid>
      <description>This post is part of the series maps-app.
You can also find the current state of the project under my GitHub repo mapic (including the Spanish versions).
Scope of this post When you prepare for a job interview one of the questions they always tell you to prepare is &amp;ldquo;What are you most proud of?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapa de cualquier región del mundo con R - Parte I: El mapa base</title>
      <link>https://blog.teoten.com/es/posts/2022/map_any_region_with_ggplot2_part_i/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.teoten.com/es/posts/2022/map_any_region_with_ggplot2_part_i/</guid>
      <description>Pueden encontrar todas las publicaciones en este tema bajo las series maps-app.
También pueden encontrar el estado actual del proyecto en mi GitHub repo mapic.
Sobre esta entrada Cuando nos preparamos para una entrevista de trabajo, una de las preguntas que más recomiendan preparar es &amp;ldquo;Menciona el proyecto del que estés más orgulloso?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
